Guide to the Ivan Collins Papers 1903-1971
Oregon Historical Society, Research Library
Ivan Collins Papers
1903-1971
Oregon Historical Society, Davies Family Research Library Research Library 1200 SW Park Avenue Portland, Oregon 97205 Phone: 503-306-5240 Fax: 503-219-2040 E-mail: libreference@ohs.org
Mss 2012
Collins, Ivan, 1906-1971
10 cu. ft. (11 document cases, 2 card file boxes, 2 flat boxes, 71 oversize folders).
The Ivan Collins papers, 1903-1971, document research, publication and exhibition activities pertaining to Collins's studies, construction and models of horse-drawn vehicles. The buk of the collection dates from the period from about 1940 to 1971 and includes correspondence between Collins and the other wagon research experts in the United States. Numerous newspaper and magazine clippings reflect Collins's obsession with his topic. Of particular historical interest is both the scale plans of his wagons, which provide rare construction details, and the journals, notes and sketches which document how Collins located examples to work from and how he learned to construct historically accurate models.
Biographical Note
Ivan L. Collins (1906-1971) was born in Dufur, Oregon and grew up in Wasco County. Operatic aspirations led him to Los Angeles in the 1930s. While in California, in 1935, Collins constructed a "prairie schooner" from a model kit while recovering from an illness. His dissatisfaction with the model's authenticity made him realize that correct knowledge about the design and construction of the entire range of recently "extinct" horse-drawn wagons of the nineteenth century was in danger of being entirely lost. From the late 1930s through the 1940s, while he earned his living constructing models at movie studios and as an aircraft mockup builder at Lockheed, Collins devoted his personal time and resources to researching and constructing wagons. By the end of the 1940s he had completed about forty wagons and had secured a publisher for Horse Power Days (Stanford University Press, 1953 / 388.3 C712h), an illustrated book about his work.
Collins moved his family to Eugene in 1950, where he worked as a designer for the University of Oregon physical plant. His ongoing avocation of model wagon building found a home at the University in 1965 when he retired to half time at the Physical Plant and became director and curator of the incipient wagon museum. He continued building and researching until his death in February 1971. Shortly thereafter, his family donated his collection and research to the Oregon Historical Society.
The Ivan Collins papers, 1903-1971, document research, publication and exhibition activities pertaining to Collins' studies, construction and models of horse-drawn vehicles. The collection concentrates on the period from about 1940 to 1971. Much of the collection preserves correspondence between Collins and the other wagon research experts in the United States. Numerous newspaper and magazine clippings reflect Collins' obsession with his topic. Of particular historical interest is both the scale plans of his wagons, which hold specific construction details that are now difficult to find, and the journals, notes and sketches which document how Collins located examples to work from and how he learned to construct historically accurate models.
Included at the end of the collection is a series of reproductions of the Collins drawings, including negatives, for reference use.
Series I.: Model Plans, 1938-1970.
Series II: Model Research, 1908-1970.
Series III: Topical, 1903-1971.
Series IV: Museums and Exhibits, 1946-1971.
Series V: Research and Clippings, 1965-1970.
Series VI: Reference Reproductions, undated.
Reproductions of selected scale drawings from the Ivan Collins papers can be purchased from the Oregon Historical Society Press, 1200 SW Park Avenue, Portland, OR 97205, (503) 222-1741.
The collection is open to the public.
Gift of Ivan Collins.
Collins, Ivan L. Horse power days: popular vehicles of nineteenth century America / made and described by Ivan L. Collins; with photographs by Ivan L. and Laura Collins.
The collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings:
Collins, Ivan, 1906-1971; Wagons —West (U.S.)—Models.; Carriages and carts —West (U.S.)—Models.; Horse-drawn vehicles —West (U.S.)—Models.; Models and modelmaking.; Clippings.; Correspondence; Drawings.; Negatives.; Scale drawings.; Scrapbooks.; Transportation; Photographs; Scrapbooks
Contents List
- Model Plans, 1938-1970; Series I:; 2 cubic feet.
  Drawings of wagons, many taken in the field by Collins, arranged by wagon type.
  - Plans - Concord Coach, 1828-1900 (Box-folder Oversize/2012-1)
    Plans - Framing details for full-scale Concord Coach
    Plans - Concord Coach by L. Downing & Sons - believed built about 1853 before the firm was again united as Abbot, Downing Co. - drafting begun April 20, 1942 - running gear completed July 25, 1942.
    80 drawings on 5 sheets, one fragment, assorted sizes, 32 x 39 to 73 x 92 cm.
    Duplicates: 16, blueline and brownline, 71 x 90 cm.
    Scale: assorted (1/8":1" to 1/2":1").
    Also 2 sheets mylar copies, 77 x 96 cm..
    See also boxes 12 & 13 and box 11 folder 19
  - Plans - [Conestoga Wagon] (Box-folder Oversize/2102-2)
    Plans - Conestoga Wagon - 1725 - compiled from Landis Valley Museum collection, Los Angeles Historical Museum and "Conestoga Six Horse Bell Teams" by John Omwake
    Plans - [Conestoga Wagon]
    27 drawings on 3 sheets, assorted sizes, 48 x 61 to 127 x 57 cm.
    Scale: (1 1/2":1' and 1":1')
    Pencil and blueline
    See also boxes 12 & 13 and box 10 folder 22
  - Plans - Coupe Rockaway - from complete working drawings with 21 illustrations in volume XVIII 1882-83 Carriage Monthly - November 10, 1949 (Box-folder Oversize/2012-3)
    5 drawings on 1 sheet, 54 x 79 cm.
    Scale not given.
    Pencil.
    See also boxes 12 & 13 and box 11 folder 22
  - Plans—Army Covered Wagon—Civil War period for six mules—prepared for the museum labratory[sic] National Park Service (Box-folder Oversize/2012-4)
    8 drawings on 1 sheet, 54 x 116 cm
    Scale: (1 1/2":1')
    Blueline.
  - Plans—Bakery Wagon—original owned by Williams Bakery, Eugene, Ore. - July 11, 1949 (Box-folder Oversize/2012-5)
    3 drawings on 1 sheet, 41 x 87 cm.
  - Plans—Buck Board—1850—Eugene, Oregon (Box-folder Oversize/2012-6)
    OrHi 35845
    3 drawings on 1 sheet, 49 x 61 cm.
    See also boxes 12 & 13 and box 10 folder 4
  - Plans—Brewery Wagon (Box-folder Oversize/2012-7)
    2 drawings on 1 sheet, 49 x 61 cm.
    See also boxes 12 & 13 and box 11 folder 11
  - Plans—Brougham—model completed Feb. 14, 1941 (Box-folder Oversize/2012-8)
    4 drawings on 1 sheet, 48 x 61 cm.
    See also boxes 12 & 13 and box 11 folder 24
  - Plans—Balloon Gas Wagon (Box-folder Oversize/2012-9)
    See also boxes 12 & 13 and box 10 folder 29
  - Plans—"Birdsell" Mountain Wagon—draft from details in R. M. Wade & Co. catalogue—Sept. 23, 1945 (Box-folder Oversize/2012-10)
    OrHi 37961
    5 drawings on 1 sheet, 64 x 92 cm.
    Duplicates: 5, blueline and brownline, 64 x 93 cm.
    Scale: (1/8":1")
    See also boxes 12 & 13 and box 10 folder 33
  - Plans—(Vis-A-Vis) Break (c. 1900)—manufactured by Hooker & Co., New Haven, Conn. Gift of Nion Tucker family, Rogue River, Oregon, to Jacksonville Museum, Jacksonville, Oregon—field drawings & notes Sept. 16, 1967, final drawing Sept. 20-27, 1967—Museum of Wagons, University of Oregon (Box-folder Oversize/2012-11)
    11 drawings on 1 sheet, 66 x 92 cm.
    Duplicates: 2, blueline, 64 x 93 cm.
    See also boxes 12 & 13 and box 11 folder 14
  - Plans—Barouche—1862, T. E. Baldwin & Co. 786 B'way N.Y.—drafted Nov. 7, 1943 (Box-folder Oversize/2012-12)
    5 drawings on 1 sheet, 78 x 58 cm.
    See also boxes 12 & 13 and box 10 folder 21
  - Plans—Dump Wagon—original manufactured by Bain Wagon Co., Kenosha, Wis. circa 1895—drawings made from original wagon at Rancho El Providencia, Los Angeles—12/17/44 & 9/20/58 (Box-folder Oversize/2012-13)
    18 drawings on 2 sheets, 63 x 113 and 68 x 116 cm.
    See also boxes 12 & 13 and box 10 folder 26
  - Plans—Bundle Rack—field notes made at E. M. Burtner Ranch, Dufur, Oregon, July 16, 1966—University of Oregon—7/21/66 (Box-folder Oversize/2012-14)
    4 drawings on 1 sheet, 63 x 93 cm.
    Duplicates: 3, blueline, 61 x 93 cm.
  - Plans—Dump Wagon "The Bain"—cement-lime-rock-sand—original owner Frank Drasman—drafted Dec. 17, 1944 at Rancho El Providencia (Box-folder Oversize/2012-15)
    Plans—Dump Wagon "The Bain" [dimensions overlayed from Bain Wagon owned by Joe Morreli, Shaniko Hotel, Shaniko, Oregon—sketched 9/3/64]
    4 drawings on 1 sheet, 65 x 93 cm.
    Dimensions overlayed on Birdsell plans.
    Blueline with pencil.
    See also boxes 12 & 13 and box 10 folder 25
  - Plans—Drummer's Wagon—started Feb. 14, 1941—completed April 21, 1941 (running gear completed) March 3, 1941 (Box-folder Oversize/2012-16)
    2 drawings on 1 sheet, 48 x 61 cm.
    See also boxes 12 & 13 and box 11 folder 8
  - Plans—"Link" Dray—original at Pierce Miller Ranch, Modesto, California—field drawings & notes, July 17, 1970—final drawing completed, October 30, 1970—University of Oregon (Box-folder Oversize/2012-17)
    Plans—Link Dray—Modesto, Cal—preliminary drawing—7/10/70
    1 drawing, 1 positive copy
    8 drawings on 2 sheets, 74 x 92 and 79 x 112 cm.
    Duplicates: 2, blackline and blueline, 74 x 111 cm.
  - Plans—Standard New York Delivery Wagon—original mfgr: Hoepfner & Co 47 Bayard St. New York—circa 1885-1898—model 47—April 7, 1956 (Box-folder Oversize/2012-18)
    5 drawings on 1 sheet, 69 x 101 cm.
    See also boxes 12 & 13 and box 11 folder 15
  - Plans—(Adams) Express Truck—drafted at Rancho El Providencia, Los Angeles, Calif—Feb. 5, 1947 (Box-folder Oversize/2012-19)
    5 drawings on 1 sheet, 70 x 126 cm.
  - Plans—Express Wagon—drafted June 8, 1945—city stables, Eugene, Oregon (Box-folder Oversize/2012-20)
    4 drawings on 1 sheet, 63 x 83 cm.
    See also boxes 12 & 13 and box 10 folder 11
  - Plans—(Armours) Express Wagon (Box-folder Oversize/2012-21)
    Plans—[(Armours) Express Wagon]
    8 drawings on 2 sheets, 31 x 45 cm.
    See also boxes 12 & 13 and box 11 folder 10
  - Plans—Freight (Boiler) Wagon—from Coffman photograph—at Portland, Oregon—1906—logging gear detail from The Dalles Museum & Fish Bros. wagon catalog—Museum of Wagons, University of Oregon—field drawings (The Dalles) May 11-12, 1968 - May 23, 1968 (Box-folder Oversize/2012-22)
    6 drawings on 1 sheet, 70 x 93 cm.
    Duplicate: 1, blueline, 67 x 90 cm.
    See also boxes 12 & 13 and box 10 folder 24
  - Plans—Fuel Wagon—1900-1928—Holman Fuel Company, Portland, Oregon—field drawings 9-20-68, Shaniko, Oregon—final drawings 3-7-69—Museum of Wagons, U of O (Box-folder Oversize/2012-23)
    5 drawings on 1 sheet, 66 x 93 cm.
    Duplicate: 1, blueline, 66 x 93 cm.
    See also boxes 12 & 13 and box 10 folder 15
  - Plans—Fire Department Hose Wagon—original owned by Wesley W. Jung, Sheboygan, Wisconsin—notes: June 1969—photos: May 1970—drawing completed: May 22, 1970 (Box-folder Oversize/2012-24)
    4 drawings on 1 sheet, 68 x 91 cm.
    Duplicate: 1, blueline, 64 x 90 cm.
    See also boxes 12 & 13 and box 11 folder 4
  - Plans—Civil War Field Piece—drafted at Overland Stables, Culver City, Calif. 3/11/45 (Box-folder Oversize/2012-25)
    8 drawings on 1 sheet, 65 x 115 cm.
    See also boxes 12 & 13 and box 10 folder 28
  - Plans—Garbage Wagon—California State Park, Coloma, California—field drawings, July 17, 1970, Oct. 27, 1970 (corrected)—final drawings, Nov. 20, 1970—University of Oregon Wagon Museum (Box-folder Oversize/2012-26)
    Plans—Garbage Wagon—Coloma, Calif—preliminary drawing—7/8/70
    4 drawings on 1 sheet, 75 x 113 cm.
    Duplicates: 5, blueline, 76 c 103 cm.
    Scale: (1/8":1')
    Also 1 sheet preliminary drawings, pencil, 76 x 92 cm. and 1 sheet obsolete drawings, blueline, 73 x 105 cm.
  - Plans—Goose-Neck Van—1894—The Dalles, Oregon (Box-folder Oversize/2012-27)
    4 drawings on 1 sheet, 49 x 61 cm.
    See also boxes 12 & 13 and box 10 folder 12
  - Plans—Governess Cart (Box-folder Oversize/2012-28)
    2 drawings on 1 sheet, 45 x 60 cm.
    See also boxes 12 & 13 and box 10 folder 13
  - Plans—Grain Wagon—Mitchell-Lewis & Co. Running Gear—field notes made at Merril Adkisson Ranch near Dufur, Oregon, Aug. 29, 1965-Feb. 4, 1966—University of Oregon (Box-folder Oversize/2012-29)
    4 drawings on 1 sheet, 65 x 86 cm.
    Duplicate: 1, blueline, 62 x 85 cm.
    See also boxes 12 & 13 and box 11 folder 17
  - Plans—Hansom Cab—purchased 1894 from J. A. Lawton & Co, London & Liverpool—drafted Los Angeles, Nov. 29, 1942—model completed Wed. March 17, 1943 (Box-folder Oversize/2012-30)
    3 drawings on 1 sheet, 57 x 78 cm.
    See also boxes 12 & 13 and box 11 folder 25
  - Plans—Ice Wagon—sketched at Rancho El Providencia 12/29/46—drawn Jan. 16, 1947 (Box-folder Oversize/2012-31)
    3 drawings on 1 sheet, 41 x 91 cm.
    See also boxes 12 & 13 and box 11 folder 12
  - Plans—Ladder Truck—original model owned by 20th Century Fox—model started Aug. 5, 1940, completed Oct. 10, 1940 (Box-folder Oversize/2012-32)
    See also boxes 12 & 13 and box 11 folder 3
  - Plans—"Slip-Reach" Log Cart—1912—Marshfield, Oregon—drawing done at Cal Young's farm, Eugene, Oregon, Dec. 1938 (Box-folder Oversize/2012-33)
    5 drawings on 1 sheet, 49 x 61 cm.
    See also boxes 12 & 13 and box 10 folder 14
  - Plans—No. 14 Streich Turntable Roll-Off/Lumber Wagon—original owned by William Gannon, Mabton, Washington—drawn...Jan. 10, 1965—field drawings & notes, July 20, 1964 (Box-folder Oversize/2012-34)
    8 drawings on 1 sheet, 61 x 89 cm.
    Duplicates: 6, blueline and brownline, 62 x 90 cm.
    See also boxes 12 & 13 and box 10 folder 17
  - Plans—Milk Wagon—original owned by 20th Century Fox—drafted Sept. 23, 1944 (Box-folder Oversize/2012-35)
    3 drawings on 1 sheet, 64 x 99 cm.
    See also boxes 12 & 13 and box 11 folder 9
  - Plans—Eastern Oregon Type Wagon Bed/Lumber Wagon (Box-folder Oversize/2012-36)
    10 drawings on 1 sheet, 39 x 49 cm.
    See also boxes 12 & 13 and box 10 folder 16
  - Plans—Pleasure Wagon c. 1825 (Box-folder Oversize/2012-37)
    Original acquired by Yakima Museum, Yakima, Washington—field drawings—March 21-22, 1969—final drawing completed April 2, 1969—Museum of Wagons U of O
    6 drawings on 1 sheet, 64 x 92 cm.
    Duplicates: 5, blueline, 61 x 93 cm.
  - Plans—Working drawings of Physicians' Phaeton [copied from The Hub, February 1, 1884] (Box-folder Oversize/2012-38)
    8 drawings on 1 sheet, 68 x 90 cm.
    Duplicates: 4, blackline and blueline, 62 x 65 to 66 x 91 cm
    Scale: (1":1')
    Blackline.
    See also boxes 12 & 13 and box 11 folder 13
  - Plans—Red River Cart, 1801-c.1880—(North Dakota-Canada) Smithsonian Institution, Washington, D. C.—field drawings, June 10, 1969—final drawings, March 20, 1970—University of Oregon Wagon Museum (Box-folder Oversize/2012-39)
    5 drawings on 1 sheet, 59 x 79 cm.
    Duplicates: 2, blueline, 57 x 77 cm.
    See also boxes 12 & 13 and box 10 folder 23
  - Plans—Road Coach, 1825-1917—Wagons of America in Miniature—11/12/59 (Box-folder Oversize/2012-40)
    10 drawings on 1 sheet, 73 x 93 cm.
    Duplicate: 1, blueline, 72 x 94 cm.
    See also boxes 12 & 13 and box 10 folder 31
  - Plans—Surrey—drafted Burbank, Calif., March 28, 1943—model begun April 5, 1943—completed (Box-folder Oversize/2012-41)
    OrHi 35843
    2 drawings on 1 sheet, 52 x 78 cm.
    See also boxes 12 & 13 and box 10 folder 20
  - Plans—Sprinkler Wagon (1900-1910)—manufactured by Studebaker Bros. Mfg. Co., South Bend, Indiana—operated in Klamath Falls, Oregon c. 1910—reconditioned for Klamath County Museum by Scott Warren 1968-1969—field drawings, Aug. 1, 2, 1969—final drawings, Aug. 21, 1969—University of Oregon Wagon Museum (Box-folder Oversize/2012-42)
    9 drawings on 1 sheet, 73 x 92 cm.
    Duplicates: 2, blueline, 70 x 89 cm.
    See also boxes 12 & 13 and box 11 folder 5
  - Plans—Wheeled Scraper—compiled from illustrations and dimension P & O catalog, page 254—Dec. 30, 1946 (Box-folder Oversize/2012-43)
    2 drawings on 1 sheet, 46 x 61 cm.
    See also boxes 12 & 13 and box 10 folder 27
  - Plans—Sheepherder's Wagon—original owned by Mrs. Clara Howard, Klamath Falls, Oregon—Mf'd by Stevens Implement Company, Ogden, Utah c. 1912—field drawings, June 2, 1968—final drawings, August 29, 1968—Museum of Wagons University of Oregon (Box-folder Oversize/2012-44)
    12 drawings on 1 sheet, 67 x 102 cm.
    Duplicate: 1, blueline, 64 x 101 cm.
    See also boxes 12 & 13 and box 11 folder 18
  - Plans—Six Passenger Albany Sleigh c. 1885—prototype owned by Mr. John E. Jaqua, Eugene, Oregon (1967)—field drawings, April 12-14, 1967—final drawing, April 21-24, 1967—University of Oregon (Box-folder Oversize/2012-45)
    6 drawings on 1 sheet, 64 x 90 cm.
    Duplicate: 1, blueline, 61 x 87 cm.
    See also boxes 12 & 13 and box 11 folder 1
  - Plans—Oscillating Bobsled—at Magna, Utah—drafted July 25, 1945 (Box-folder Oversize/2012-46)
    4 drawings on 1 sheet, 70 x 103 cm.
    See also boxes 12 & 13 and box 10 folder 8
  - Plans—Union Oil Company Tank Wagon—now the property of 20th Century Fox Film Corporation, Beverly Hills, Calif.—drafted July 15-16, 1944 (Box-folder Oversize/2012-47)
    4 drawings on 1 sheet, 62 x 117 cm.
    Duplicate: 1, blueline.
    See also boxes 12 & 13 and box 10 folder 6
  - Plans—Wagonette—owned by Hillcrest Orchards, Medford, Oregon—field drawings made August 24-25, 1966—final drawings made Sept. 21-23, 1966—U of O (Box-folder Oversize/2012-48)
    OrHi 35841
    5 drawings on 1 sheet, 65 x 91 cm.
    Duplicates: 4, blueline, 66 x 93 cm.
    See also boxes 12 & 13 and box 11 folder 6
  - Plans—[Plow] (Box-folder Oversize/2012-49)
    1 drawing on 1 sheet, 36 x 35 cm.
    Ink.
  - Plans—[Hose Wagon] (Box-folder Oversize/2012-50)
    Plans—[Hose Wagon]
    3 drawings on 2 sheets, 46 x 61 and 49 x 61 cm.
  - Plans—Hearse, circa 1900—original mfg. by Sayers & Scoville Co., Cincinnati, Ohio—drawings made from vehicle at Eugene, Oregon, Oct. 1940—redrawn Nov. 1958 (Box-folder Oversize/2012-51)
    14 drawings on 1 sheet, 75 x 106 cm.
    See also boxes 12 & 13 and box 10 folder 32
  - Plans—Yellowstone Transportation Co. Coach—drafted at Rancho El Providencia, Los Angeles, Calif.—September 29, 1946 (Box-folder Oversize/2012-52)
    4 drawings on 1 sheet, 105 x 63 cm.
    See also boxes 12 & 13 and box 11 folder 20
  - Plans—Army Escort Wagon, 1918—built by John Deere Plow Co., Moline, Ill.—drafted July 25th 1943—model started July 27, 1943—completed Sept 27, [1943] (Box-folder Oversize/2012-53)
    4 drawings on 1 sheet, 59 x 82 cm.
    See also boxes 12 & 13 and box 10 folder 5
  - Plans—Omnibus for Umatilla House—drafted June 7, 1943 at The Dalles, Oregon. My father assisted me in taking the measurements—completed Jan. 17, 1943 (Box-folder Oversize/2012-54)
    4 drawings on 1 sheet, 56 x 78 cm.
    See also boxes 12 & 13 and box 11 folder 23
  - Plans—Medicine Wagon—completed April 14, 1942 (Box-folder Oversize/2012-55)
    3 drawings on 1 sheet, 46 x 62 cm.
    See also boxes 12 & 13 and box 11 folder 7
  - Plans—Exhibit Case Assemblies-Museum of Fine Arts—5/24/54 (Box-folder Oversize/2012-56)
    7 drawings & stock bill on 1 sheet, 75 x 89 cm.
    Duplicates: 2, blueline, 76 x 90 cm.
    Scale: assorted (half size to full size)
    Brownline.
  - Plans—Exhibition Case Layout-Gallery U of O Memorial Union—5/7/59 (Box-folder Oversize/2012-57)
    Plans—Proposed Layout for the Ivan L. Collins Miniature Wagon Exhibition-Gallery U of O Memorial Union—1/10/55
    Plans—Exhibit Cases-Student Union—2/16/57
    14 drawings & stock bill on 2 sheets, 29 x 66 and 76 x 95 cm.
    Duplicates: 4, blueline; 5, blackline and blueline for 1955 exhibition, 75 x 95 cm.
    Scale: assorted (1/4":1' to 1":1')
    See also box 8 folders 7 & 8
  - Plans—Partial Plan First Addition Erb Memorial Student Union—10/1/64 (Box-folder Oversize/2012-58)
    1 drawing on 1 sheet, 46 x 75 cm.
    Duplicates: 2, blackline, 46 x 75 cm.
    Scale: (1/4":1')
  - Plans—Exposition Building-Wagon Layout (Box-folder Oversize/2012-59)
    1 drawing on 1 sheet, 55 x 84 cm.
    Duplicate: 1, blueline, 55 x 84 cm.
  - Plans—Space Requirements & Suggested Layout for Wagon Exhibition-Meier & Frank Auditorium—3/15/57 (Box-folder Oversize/2012-60)
    3 drawings on 1 sheet, 55 x 97 cm.
    See also box 8 folder 3
  - Plans—Exhibition Case Requirements October (1954) Exhibition O.S.C. Memorial Union: sheet I (Box-folder Oversize/2012-61)
    Plans—Proposed Layout for the Exhibition of the Ivan L. Collins Collection of Historic Wagons in Miniature—October 1954: sheet II
    8 drawings, with specifications, on 2 sheets, 31 x 83 and 69 x 85 cm.
    See also box 8 folder 4
  - Drawing/plan—Fire Station (Box-folder Oversize/2012-62)
    3 drawings on 1 sheet, 49 x 92 cm.
    Scale: (1/8 size)
  - Sketch—design for cutter (Box-folder Oversize/2012-63)
    1 drawing on 1 sheet, 42 x 54 cm.
    See also boxes 12 & 13 and box 10 folder 10
  - Plans—Storage Case No. 5—5/5/70 (Box-folder Oversize/2012-64)
    Plans—Wagon Museum Display Case—9/5/69
    12 drawings on 2 sheets, 45 x 75 and 70 x 62 cm.
    Pencil and blueline.
  - Drawing—Victoria—Zenz Bros.—by W.E. Miller 12-20-39 (Box-folder Oversize/2012-65)
    OrHi 35846
    1 drawing on 1 sheet.
    See also boxes 12 & 13 and box 11 folder 2
- Model research, 1938-1970; Series II:; 1.5 cubic feet.
  Newspaper clippings, magazine articles, notes and sketches used by Collins while researching wagons.
  Arranged alphabetically by wagon type.
  - Automobile, undated (Box-folder 1/1)
    2 newspaper items
  - Bain Wagon, 1964-1966 (Box-folder 1/2)
    sketch of Bain Wagon details by Margaret E. Collins, advertisement, letter.
    See also boxes 12 & 13, oversize 2012-15, and box 10 folder 25.
  - Bakery Window, 1949 (Box-folder 1/3)
    2 newspaper photographs, notes, postcard, letter
  - Balloon Gas Wagon, 1940-1959 (Box-folder 1/4)
    3 letters, 5 magazine items, 2 newspaper items, notes, transcript, 3 photographs, 3 drawings.
    See also boxes 12 & 13, oversize 2012-9, and box 10 folder 29
  - Barouche, undated (Box-folder 1/5)
    newspaper item, magazine item, letter, notes.
    See also boxes 12 & 13, oversize 2012-12, and box 10 folder 21.
  - Boiler Wagon, undated (Box-folder 1/6)
    reprint cover of Frank Leslie's Illustrated Newspaper, April 12, 1879, notes, sketches of details.
    See also boxes 12 & 13, oversize 2012-22, and box 10 folder 6.
  - Borax Wagon, undated (Box-folder 1/7)
    Magazine item, magazine photograph
  - Brewery Wagon, undated (Box-folder 1/8)
    Newspaper item.
    See also boxes 12 & 13, oversize 2012-7, and box 10 folder 8.
  - Break Wagon, 1947, 1967 (Box-folder 1/9)
    Notes, 8 letters, sketches of details, wagon price list.
    See also boxes 12 & 13, oversize 2012-11, and box 11 folder 14.
  - Brougham, undated (Box-folder 1/10)
    Notes, magazine advertisement.
    See also boxes 12 & 13, oversize 2012-8, and box 11 folder 24.
  - Buckboard, undated (Box-folder 1/11)
    2 magazine items.
    See also boxes 12 & 13, oversize 2012-6, and box 10 folder 4.
  - Buggy, undated (Box-folder 1/12)
    Advertisement, sketches of details, magazine item, newspaper photograph.
  - Bundle Rack, Dufur, undated (Box-folder 1/13)
    Sketches of bundle rack details, newspaper item, notes.
    See also boxes 12 & 13, oversize 2012-14.
  - Cable Cars, 1945, 1953, 1965 (Box-folder 1/14)
    postcard, 5 letters, pamphlet
  - Cabriolet, undated (Box-folder 1/15)
    Fabric sample, sketches of details, newspaper item, note